# 

# Simon J. Murphy

#### **Current Position**

July 2020- Casual Academic, School of Science, UNSW Canberra

As a physics tutor and laboratory demonstrator I lead first-year tutorial classes and supervise weekly laboratory sessions where students learn the fundamentals of the subject. I have also developed second-year astrophysics laboratory projects on the Sun and Eclipsing Binary stars, and supervised a short undergraduate research project.

My own research is focused on identifying and characterising some of the youngest stars in the Solar neighbourhood using a variety of observational techniques. These young, nearby systems are ideal laboratories for understanding early stellar evolution and probing the diverse conditions under which stars and, importantly, *planets* form.

# **Professional History**

2019-2020	Postdoctoral Researcher, School of Science, UNSW Canberra
2016-2019	Vice Chancellor's Postdoctoral Fellow, School of Science, UNSW Canberra
2015	SkyMapper Postdoctoral Fellow, Research School of Astronomy & Astrophysics, ANU
2013-2014	Gliese Fellow, Astronomisches Rechen-Institut, University of Heidelberg, Germany
2012	Postdoctoral Fellow, Research School of Astronomy & Astrophysics, ANU

### **Education**

2007-2011	Ph.D., Australian National University, Canberra (awarded July 13, 2012)
thesis	"Revealing the Chamaeleon: Young, low-mass stars surrounding $\eta$ and $\epsilon$ Chamaeleontis"
supervisor	Professor Michael Bessell (ANU)
2006	B.Sc. (First Class Honours), Australian National University, Canberra
2003-2005	B.Sc. (Astronomy), University of Canterbury, Christchurch, New Zealand

# **Teaching Experience**

2021	Tutor and lab demonstrator, ZEPM1501 Physics 1A, UNSW Canberra
2020	Tutor and lab demonstrator, ZPEM15O1(2) Physics 1A(B), UNSW Canberra
	Lab demonstrator, ZPEM2509 Astrophysics, UNSW Canberra
	I developed two online labs on the Sun and Eclipsing Binary stars
	Supervisor, ZPEM1901 Contemporary Issues in Science, UNSW Canberra, (4 week first-year research project for CDF students)

# **Publication Summary**

2008- Refereed publications: **35** (32 in UNSW Q1 journals) First-author publications: **8** Second-author: **5** 

Career h-index: **20** (h publications with at least h citations)

Career citations: 1166; via NASA ADS.

### **Research Interests**

- o Low-mass star formation and early stellar evolution
- o Accretion and circumstellar disc evolution
- Stellar age diagnostics
- o Eclipsing binaries as tests of stellar models
- o Star clusters, moving groups and associations
  - New members (especially at lowest masses)
  - Stellar kinematics, dynamical evolution of young groups
- o Data science; knowledge discovery from large data sets
- o Scientific exploitation of the global Virtual Observatory initiative

# **Key Research Proficiencies**

- o Development and exploitation of large astronomical databases (e.g. SkyMapper)
- Analysis of stellar age diagnostics
- o Extensive programming experience (Python–expert, web, databases, Perl, Javascript)
- Optical spectroscopy (low-high resolution)
- o Integral-field spectroscopy and data reduction
- o Optical imaging and photometry
- Applications of stellar and Galactic kinematics
- o Astronomical data reduction packages (incl. IRAF, PyRAF, Figaro)
- o Development and use of Virtual Observatory tools and web services

### **Selected Awards & Prizes**

2016-2019	Vice Chancellor's Postdoctoral Fellowship, University of New South Wales
2013-2014	Gliese Postdoctoral Fellowship, University of Heidelberg
2012	Honourable Mention, ASA Charlene Heisler Prize for best Australian astronomy thesis
2007-2011	Joan Duffield Research Scholarship, ANU
2011	Vice Chancellor's Award for Community Outreach, ANU
2007	Vice Chancellor's Special Award for Outreach, ANU
2006	Bart J. Bok Honours Year Scholarship, ANU

### **Refereed Publications**

As of May 2021 I am an author of **35** peer-reviewed articles, including **13 first or second author** publications.

Career h-index: 20 (h publications with at least h citations).

Career citations: 1166; via NASA ADS.

NB: My research output was reduced in 2017-2018 as I took leave and moved to part-time hours (0.6 FTE, then 0.8 FTE until June 2020) following the birth of my first child.

- Magnetorotational hypernovae are another astronomical r-process site
   Yong, D., Kobayashi, C., Da Costa, G. S., Bessell, M. S., Chiti, A., Frebel, A., Lind, K., Mackey,
   A. D., Nordlander, T., Asplund, M., Casey, A. R., Marino, A. F., Murphy, S. J., & Schmidt, B. P.
   Accepted for publication in Nature (4 May), 2021.
  - Exploring the Galaxy's halo and very metal-weak thick disc with SkyMapper and Gaia DR2
     Cordoni, G., Da Costa, G. S., Yong, D., Mackey, A. D., Marino, A. F., Monty, S., Nordlander, T.,
     Norris, J. E., Asplund, M., Bessell, M. S., Casey, A. R., Frebel, A., Lind, K., Murphy, S. J., et al.
     Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2021, 503(2), 2539.
- THOR 42: A touchstone ~24 Myr-old eclipsing binary spanning the fully convective boundary Murphy, S. J., Lawson, W. A., Onken, C. A., Yong, D., Da Costa, G. S., Zhou, G., Mamajek, E. E., Bell, C. P. M., Bessell, M. S., & Feinstein, A. D. Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2020, 491(4), 4902.
  - Sporadic and intense accretion in a 1 Myr-old brown dwarf candidate Nguyen-Thanh, D., Phan-Bao, N., <u>Murphy, S. J.</u>, & Bessell, M. S. Astronomy & Astrophysics, 2020, 634, A128.
  - 2MASS J15460752-6258042: a mid-M dwarf hosting a prolonged accretion disc Lee, J., Song, I., & Murphy, S.
     Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2020, 494(1), 62.
  - The closest extremely low-mass white dwarf to the Sun
    Kawka, A., Simpson, J. D., Vennes, S., Bessell, M. S., Da Costa, G. S., Marino, A. F., &
    Murphy, S. J.
    Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2020, 495(1), L129.
  - A kinematically unbiased, all-sky search for nearby, young, low-mass stars
    Binks, A. S., Chalifour, M., Kastner, J. H., Rodriguez, D., Murphy, S. J., Principe, D. A., Punzi, K.,
    Sacco, G. G., & Hernández, J.
    Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2020, 491(1), 215.
- The lowest detected stellar Fe abundance: the halo star SMSS J160540.18-144323.1 Nordlander, T., Bessell, M. S., Da Costa, G. S., Mackey, A. D., Asplund, M., Casey, A. R., Chiti, A., Ezzeddine, R., Frebel, A., Lind, K., Marino, A. F., Murphy, S. J., Norris, J. E., Schmidt, B. P., & Yong, D.
  Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2019, 488(1), L109.
  - Keck HIRES spectroscopy of SkyMapper commissioning survey candidate extremely metal-poor stars
     Marino, A. F., Da Costa, G. S., Casey, A. R., Asplund, M., Bessell, M. S., Frebel, A., Keller, S. C., Lind, K., Mackey, A. D., Murphy, S. J., Nordlander, T., Norris, J. E., Schmidt, B. P., & Yong, D.

Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2019, 485(4), 5153.

- Detection of a giant flare displaying quasi-periodic pulsations from a pre-main-sequence M star by the Next Generation Transit Survey
  - Jackman, J. A. G., Wheatley, P. J., Pugh, C. E., Kolotkov, D. Y., Broomhall, A.-M., Kennedy, G. M., **Murphy, S. J.**, et al.
  - Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2019, 482(4), 5553.
- The Planet Formation Potential around a 45 Myr Old Accreting M Dwarf Flaherty, K., Hughes, A. M., Mamajek, E. E., & Murphy, S. J. Astrophysical Journal, 2019, 872(1), 92.
- The SkyMapper DR1.1 search for extremely metal-poor stars
   Da Costa, G. S., Bessell, M. S., Mackey, A. D., Nordlander, T., Asplund, M., Casey, A. R., Frebel, A., Lind, K., Marino, A. F., Murphy, S. J., Norris, J. E., Schmidt, B. P., & Yong, D. Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2019, 489(4), 5900.
- SkyMapper Southern Survey: First Data Release (DR1)
   Wolf, C., Onken, C. A., Luvaul, L. C., Schmidt, B. P., Bessell, M. S., Chang, S.-W., Da Costa, G. S., Mackey, D., Martin-Jones, T., Murphy, S. J., et al.
   Publications of the Astronomical Society of Australia, 2018, 35, e010.
  - WISE J080822.18-644357.3 a 45 Myr-old accreting M dwarf hosting a primordial disc Murphy, S. J., Mamajek, E. E., & Bell, C. P. M.
     Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2018, 476, 3290.
- A stellar census of the nearby, young 32 Orionis group
   Bell, C. P. M., Murphy, S. J., & Mamajek, E. E.
   Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2017, 468, 1198.
- A nearby young M dwarf with a wide, possibly planetary-mass companion Deacon, N. R., Schlieder, J. E., & Murphy, S. J.
   Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2016, 457, 3191.
  - The ANU WiFeS SuperNovA Programme (AWSNAP)
     Childress, M. J., Tucker, B. E., Yuan, F., Scalzo, R., Ruiter, A., Seitenzahl, I., Zhang, B., Schmidt, B., Anguiano, B., Aniyan, S., Bayliss, D. D. R., Bento, J., Bessell, M., Bian, F., Davies, R., Dopita, M., Fogarty, L., Fraser-McKelvie, A., Freeman, K., Kuruwita, R., Medling, A. M., Murphy, S. J., et al.
    - Publications of the Astronomical Society of Australia, 2016, 33, e055.
- New members of the TW Hydrae Association and two accreting M-dwarfs in Scorpius-Centaurus Murphy, S. J., Lawson, W. A., & Bento, J.
   Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2015, 453, 2220.
  - A 0.24+0.18 M<sub>☉</sub> double-lined eclipsing binary from the HATSouth survey Zhou, G., Bayliss, D., Hartman, J. D., Rabus, M., Bakos, G. Á., Jordán, A., Brahm, R., Penev, K., Csubry, Z., Mancini, L., Espinoza, N., de Val-Borro, M., Bhatti, W., Ciceri, S., Henning, T., Schmidt, B., Murphy, S. J., et al. Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2015, 451, 2263.
  - New low-mass members of the Octans stellar association and an updated 30-40 Myr lithium age

Murphy, S. J. & Lawson, W. A.

Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2015, 447, 1267.

Evolution from protoplanetary to debris discs: the transition disc around HD 166191
 Kennedy, G. M., Murphy, S. J., Lisse, C. M., Ménard, F., Sitko, M. L., Wyatt, M. C., Bayliss, D. D. R., DeMeo, F. E., Crawford, K. B., Kim, D. L., Rudy, R. J., Russell, R. W., Sibthorpe, B., Skinner, M. A., & Zhou, G.
 Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2014, 438, 3299.

4/5

- Copious Amounts of Hot and Cold Dust Orbiting the Main Sequence A-type Stars HD 131488 and HD 121191
  - Melis, C., Zuckerman, B., Rhee, J. H., Song, I., <u>Murphy, S. J.</u>, & Bessell, M. S. Astrophysical Journal, 2013, 778, 12.
  - Re-examining the membership and origin of the ε Cha association
     Murphy, S. J., Lawson, W. A., & Bessell, M. S.
     Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2013, 435, 1325.
  - The GALEX Nearby Young-Star Survey
     Rodriguez, D. R., Zuckerman, B., Kastner, J. H., Bessell, M. S., Faherty, J. K., & Murphy, S. J.
     Astrophysical Journal, 2013, 774, 101.
  - A High-resolution Spectroscopic Search for the Remaining Donor for Tycho's Supernova
    Kerzendorf, W. E., Yong, D., Schmidt, B. P., Simon, J. D., Jeffery, C. S., Anderson, J.,
    Podsiadlowski, P., Gal-Yam, A., Silverman, J. M., Filippenko, A. V., Nomoto, K., Murphy, S. J.,
    et al.
    Astrophysical Journal, 2013, 774, 99.
  - The Most Metal-poor Stars. I. Discovery, Data, and Atmospheric Parameters
     Norris, J. E., Bessell, M. S., Yong, D., Christlieb, N., Barklem, P. S., Asplund, M., Murphy, S. J., et al.

     Astrophysical Journal, 2013, 762, 25.
- Rapid disappearance of a warm, dusty circumstellar disk
   Melis, C., Zuckerman, B., Rhee, J. H., Song, I., Murphy, S. J., & Bessell, M. S.
   Nature, 2012, 487, 74.
  - RX J0942.7-7726AB: an isolated pre-main-sequence wide binary
     Murphy, S. J., Lawson, W. A., & Bessell, M. S.
     Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2012, 424, 625.
  - 2M1155-79 (= T Chamaeleontis B): A Low-mass, Wide-separation Companion to the nearby, "Old" T Tauri Star T Chamaeleontis
    Kastner, J. H., Thompson, E. A., Montez, R., Murphy, S. J., Bessell, M. S., & Sacco, G. Astrophysical Journal, Letters, 2012, 747, L23.
  - Spectrophotometric Libraries, Revised Photonic Passbands, and Zero Points for UBVRI, Hipparcos, and Tycho Photometry
    Bessell, M. & Murphy, S.
    Publications of the Astronomical Society of the Pacific, 2012, 124, 140.
- The Solar Neighborhood. XXVI. AP Col: The Closest (8.4 pc) Pre-main-sequence Star Riedel, A. R., Murphy, S. J., Henry, T. J., Melis, C., Jao, W.-C., & Subasavage, J. P. Astronomical Journal, 2011, 142, 104.
  - Episodic disc accretion in the halo of the 'old' pre-main-sequence cluster η Chamaeleontis
     Murphy, S. J., Lawson, W. A., Bessell, M. S., & Bayliss, D. D. R.

     Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2011, 411, L51.
- First detection of a low-mass stellar halo around the young open cluster η Chamaeleontis Murphy, S. J., Lawson, W. A., & Bessell, M. S.
   Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2010, 406, L50.
- 2009 Extending the Virgo Stellar Stream with SEKBO Survey RR Lyrae Stars Prior, S. L., Da Costa, G. S., Keller, S. C., & Murphy, S. J. Astrophysical Journal, 2009, 691, 306.
- Revealing Substructure in the Galactic Halo: The SEKBO RR Lyrae Survey Keller, S. C., Murphy, S., Prior, S., DaCosta, G., & Schmidt, B. Astrophysical Journal, 2008, 678, 851.